<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A faithful advertisement to all good patriots of the United-Provinces, in the present conjunctures since the death of the Prince of Orange. / Englished by the Dutch-copie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85064</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865541</idno>
  <idno type="VID">165774</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248495257</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E620_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206380</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865541</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99865541e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85064)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165774)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 95:E620[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A faithful advertisement to all good patriots of the United-Provinces, in the present conjunctures since the death of the Prince of Orange. / Englished by the Dutch-copie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Leyden 1650. Reprinted by W.D.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec: 18".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Netherlands --  History --  1648-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165774:1"/>
            <p>A Faithful ADVERTISEMENT TO ALL GOOD PATRIOTS OF THE United-Provinces, In the present Conjunctures since the death of the PRINCE of ORANGE.</p>
            <p>Englished by the Dutch-Copie Printed at <hi>Leyden</hi> 1650.</p>
            <p>Reprinted by <hi>W. D.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:165774:2"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <head>The Summarie, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>That their Lordships found good to send their Deputies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the respective Provinces, to that end and purpose.</p>
            <p>That the Committees of the other Provinces are earnestly desired to second the good intentions of their Lordships, by their serious Letters unto their respective Principals.</p>
            <p>That in the interim all matters concerning the State, shall bee left in their usual cours, and fundamental order of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; the several Counsels, and chief Militarie Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers remaining in their respective Commissions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions till such time, as further order shall bee taken about the whole Government by the Provinces.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165774:2"/>
            <head>THE ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <head type="sub">Dear Patriots! and upright lovers of your Countrie, the good and faithful inhabitants of the United Provinces!</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee have good caus, indeed, to bee affected with the untimelie and sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Departure of his Highness <hi>Prince William of Orange;</hi> beeing thus snatcht away from among us, in the flower of his Age, and in the midst of his Power and great Autoritie; leaving behinde him a memorable example, that neither Youth, nor Pedigree, nor anie Worldlie respect or condition, availeth ought against the stroke of death. And therefore wee ought all of us, to applie our selvs to the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our sinful courses, and praiers to God, that hee would teach us <hi>to number our daies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Praising withal, his loving kindness to us, that hee endueth the Government still with Wisdom, the spirit of Unitie, and Love, as is abundantly made apparent unto us, by the above-recited wholesom Resolutions of the Province of <hi>Holland,</hi> most unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously and cheerfully yielded unto, and embraced
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165774:3"/>in their Solemn Assemblie. And therefore praying to God Almightie, so to guide and steer the hearts of the rest of the Provinces, that they may all meet with Instructions and Resolutions answerable to the desired (the onelie indeed and most absolute) esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment of mutual love and Unitie; to the shame &amp; confusion, on the one side, of all our forrein enemies, who may change their <hi>hair</hi> for a season, though they cannot their <hi>kinde;</hi> and on the other side, that the eies of all such as were mis-led through anie base and pernicious impression, and as if <hi>Holland</hi> should have harboured anie thought or design to recede from, or desert the Union, may open their eies and see how they are abused. Shame overtake them, which coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selled the good young Prince those extremities of last Summer's Expedition; the rather for that the said Counsel intended against both this, and all the Provinces, cannot but prove now the greatest preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to the Hous of him to whom it was given. Hee himself indeed having seen som of the bad fruits thereof, whereas in lieu of love and affection, the onelie and best ligaments and props of a State, hee saw himself asspersed with all manner of cursings and reproches; and the Citie of <hi>Amsterdam</hi> (whence both the whole Countrie, and his Predecessors, had often been so mightily relieved with ships, Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, Monies, and anie thing that was in their power, as beeing the principal store-hous and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazine of the <hi>Republick</hi>) necessitated, by reason of such enterprises, to fortifie her self, to double their guards and garrison, to repair their walls and palli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadoes, and to secure the <hi>Amstel</hi> with out-works against the like attemts. Hee saw and heard the free
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165774:3"/>and high discourses that were occasioned thereby in all the Provinces against his proceedings; and how flat and cold the several procured and forced Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings were, from the respective parts in that behalf, (though they could not avoid it, seeing <hi>Amsterdam</hi> could not, but was fain to stoop) that it had better been left unperformed.</p>
            <p>And now after his death, his familie see'th, that the Provinces, and all good members of the same, do most unanimously applie themselvs to prevent the like mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, as in his life time they discovered and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered; which cannot but impair their repute and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that were wont hitherto to wield the State at their pleasure, and more absolutely indeed, then ever King did. For even the greatest flatterers of their own must confess, I appeal to their own consciences, That a free State and Republick, ought not to bee under such Wardship.</p>
            <p>Where was it ever heard, that a Creature created its Creator? that one in Commission command's them that gave it? that one writing himself <hi>Your humble servant,</hi> doth bridle and ride his Masters at pleasure?</p>
            <p>The good and faithful services of the Hous of <hi>Nassaw</hi> are gladly acknowledged by all; That Prince <hi>William</hi> did help the laying of the foundation of the State that Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> and Prince <hi>Henrie</hi> have faithfully, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously, and valiantly continued in it; that the like might have been exspected from the late young Prince.</p>
            <p>But I praie; have they not also from the beginning, sought and found their own particular interest in, and by it? was not the first rise more from Court-Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie (against the Spanish Faction and direction at <hi>Brus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels</hi>)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165774:4"/>the Common make-bate in all Courts, then from anie thing els. Doth not <hi>Borre</hi> aver, that Prince <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> knew not well in the beginning, whether hee should bee of the <hi>Lutheran,</hi> or the Reformed profession? did not hee advise that the <hi>Lutheran</hi> should hee main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined as principal? did not Prince <hi>William</hi> aim at the Sovereigntie? is not the Original Act to bee seen in the <hi>Court-Rowls</hi> of the late Prince, which hee had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from most Cities already: you may see it in <hi>Borre</hi> and <hi>Hooft.</hi> The Princes his Successors, have they ever more asserted or eased the Land in their true pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges, liberties and immunities, then the Kings did? have they ever remitted ought of their own Autoritie or interest to the State? nay have they not been <hi>sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Augustus,</hi> interesting and possessing themselvs of whatever they could, especially the giving of Patents, or Commissions; the disposing of Garrisons (which in the beginning was, and ought to bee, and in <hi>Fries<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> yet is, <hi>taliter, qualiter,</hi> in the State's hand, both for Cities and Countrie) and the whole power of the Souldierie? have they not forced a <hi>premier Noble</hi> upon <hi>Zealand,</hi> by which means they got the whole Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Province into their own hands. Did not the last Prince, but a year ago, make a change in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates of that Province, especially at <hi>Flushing,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to their customs? Did not hee in 1649, by meer autoritie and power of the Souldierie again dispossess those of <hi>Nimmegen</hi> against their will of their free Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Magistrates; which by very old privileges they claimed like other Cities of <hi>Gelderland,</hi> and now by virtue of the Peace they are to enjoie? have not all the said Princes swaied the Assemblie of the States General <hi>à la bagnette,</hi> under the rod? The like parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165774:4"/>would bee too long to rehears all, it beeing needless, and none indeed ignorant of them; none can denie, but they have all of them sought their particular Interest, pretending the publick; if you desire a fresh example, peruse but the late particular Treatise, and what conditions are put there upon the King of <hi>Spain</hi> by the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> besides what is conditioned in the general Articles of the Peace; and those statelie concessions of <hi>Turnhout,</hi> and <hi>Sevenbergen</hi> for my Ladie the Princess <hi>Dowager.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And who know's not, what honorable and prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Enterteinments, Emoluments, Profits, Pensions, Advancements, Presents and Honoraries have conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually been drawn and enjoied, as well by the Princes themselvs, as by those of their hous and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred? which is in no wise alleged here to upbraid them with; beeing a thing both equal and customa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and the style of the world; But it must bee said, to shew, that if they did great service to the State and Countrie, they were likewise most roially re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded.</p>
            <p>And for those services they performed, was it not still with and by the means of the Land? Have not the Commons been fain to gather it together with their sweat and blood? Have they ever contributed a pennie towards it, out of their own purs? Nay, have not they and their Families alwaies been exempt from all excises, impositions, and Taxations, which the least peasant and poorest inhabitant was forced to paie still? Nevertheless it was held fit and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, and I do not discommend it: I speak it not to lessen their Merit, Honor and respect; the Land sped not th worse for that.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:165774:5"/>
            <p>But in regard that som few pick-thanks here and there take upon them to discours, to the prejudice and discouragement of the Land; as if the State could not subsist, now it is destitute of a Governor; Let this serv for better information and instruction; <hi>That the true, and perfect sovereigntie is in the Republick, which never die's,</hi> and that the wisdom, prudence, concord and Love therein doth not depend upon a person. At <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>Genoa</hi> théy have a <hi>Doge</hi> or <hi>Duke,</hi> when hee dieth, they chuse another; and all is well. The thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen <hi>Swisser-Cantons</hi> are kindled and allied together, much like our seven Provinces; and though of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Religions, yet they live in peace and concord among themselvs: they know of no Governor, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-General, or stadholder; Hee that meddle's with one, doth rouz them all; they meet twice or thrice a year in a general Assemblie, consulting of such things as concern their general Weal. They lie betwixt <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stria, Venice,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> yet none dare's annoie them mainteining not onely themselvs, but their Neigbors also, as the <hi>Valtoline, Geneva, &amp;c. Bern</hi> is like unto <hi>Holland,</hi> the second in order, and greatest in power, <hi>England</hi> at present hath wars (I leav the caus and circumstances to themselvs) and therefore they must have a Head for the <hi>Militia.</hi> General <hi>Cromwel</hi> is but a member of the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> as also of the <hi>Parlament,</hi> having, nor claming no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, no not the least above his fellow-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. And do not wee daily see and hear, what migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie things are don there both by Sea and Land? The Republicks of <hi>Nurenberg, Strasburg, Ulm,</hi> and all the rest of the <hi>free Imperial Cities</hi> are governed by Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomasters
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165774:5"/>and Senators, and have maintained them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selvs in that sort for manie hundreds of years, making their own Magistrate, and knowing of no stad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, or Governor; though in case or fear of war, they chuse a Head, somtimes a Nobleman, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while one of meaner condition, a fouldier of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, to command their Forces. <hi>Embden</hi> it self, hard by us, doth practise the same, though no Imperial or free Citie. <hi>Venice, Genoa, Luca,</hi> and the <hi>Swissers</hi> do the like. But all after such a manner, that they finde it no sooner otherwise expedient, but they laie those Heads, Generals or Coronels by again, in part, or altogether, more or less: and it is so far from it, that those Militarie Heads should make anie resistance, or prescribe unto their Masters, that on the contrarie receiving their Dismission with all submission, they praie, that upon the next emergencie or opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the Magistrate would bee pleased to remember them with further Emploiment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Libertie and Freedom;</hi> of which wee had, and enjoied but the shadow here all this while.</p>
            <p>All the antient, both Greek and Romane Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks kept the same cours; employing in time of war, none but their fellow-Citizens; who when the war or expedition ceased, forthwith surrendred their charge and autoritie.</p>
            <q>Juvit sumpta Ducem, juvit demissa potestas.</q>
            <p>It was never heard of in a Republick, that there should bee a General, where there was no war; so as that hee should have the absolute Command of the State-forces, even to emploie the same against his own Masters. In the field indeed it is expedient, that the General or Coronel dispose of the Charges and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165774:6"/>Offices, by reason of sudden emergencies and acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, brooking no delaie, and that there on the place, they know best, who deserv's best. But at home they ought to bee disposed of by the Pai-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters. To saie, that a Prince doth bestow most of the Offices upon the worthiest, is ridiculous; For wee have seen with our eies; that scarce anie here get them but fawning Courtiers; the old and good soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers remained still what, and where they were. Doth it go by favor too among the Pai-masters, that is less strange; they are masters. The Princes far exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein; I have often heard Gentlemen complain, that there was scaree anie thing left for them to ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, or aspire unto, whiles the Prince's kindred was so numerous. Wee know, there can bee no perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction here on earth, and these and the like above re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearsed complaints stood daily in a multiplying con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>The Ambassadors sent over into <hi>England</hi> about the Match, made the King there believ mightie things, of I know not what Hereditarie Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentship, and mightie Assistance that King might thereupon exspect from this State.</p>
            <p>Touching the former, there need's no producing of Acts; do not wee see at this present, how upon the Princess Roial her Deliverie, the Court-spanniels prate and keep ado, as if the State was necessarily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged, there beeing a young Prince, to admit him without dispute to the charge of Governor-General, and Stadholder. Is not this claiming Inheritance and Sovereigntie? Hath there not been intimation pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented already, <hi>that these things might not bee debated. For, proceeded in they may turn to the prejudice of her issue;</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:165774:6"/>What remain's then for us to do, but that wee pass an express <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Hereditarie Governor,</hi> to make good the Ambassador's word; (though unwarranted) that so wee may the more easily bee brought likewise under that unluckie Hous of the <hi>Stuarts,</hi> which the <hi>English</hi> themselvs have shaken off, and the <hi>Scots</hi> themselvs declare, to bee <hi>full of blood and sin;</hi> although I pass no verdict on it.</p>
            <p>It will bee said, <hi>that nevertheless this rule was followed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the third Generation:</hi> it is partly true; but yet after Prince <hi>William,</hi> wee took <hi>Leicester;</hi> and after him Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> and Prince <hi>Henrie:</hi> Howbeit, it is remarkable, that hee who in those daies had the chiefest direction in the affairs of State, counted it serviceable for his turn, to devolv the Autoritie on Prince <hi>Maurice;</hi> that by the Prince, beeing but young then, and standing in need of courting again the favor of the said Director, hee might everie where supplie the Magistrates, with his Creatures; whom Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> afterwards, in the year 1618. cast all out again. Upon that ground also, and the advice of the said Director, was it that Prince <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1611. changed the Magistrate of <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trecht,</hi> and took the election to himself, as also at <hi>Alcmar,</hi> and the Election of the Common-Councel at <hi>Rotterdam.</hi> Prince <hi>Henrie</hi> likewise in 1625 was as suddenly received, without instructions: why? hee had the Republick's arms and forces in his own hands then.</p>
            <p>Upon the Birth of the late Prince <hi>William,</hi> there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared a <hi>ruere in servitium,</hi> each one strove to bee fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most in offering the survivance, or Reversion. One of <hi>Over Yessel,</hi> one of <hi>Utrecht,</hi> and a few more elswhere
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165774:7"/>knew how to manage and compass the same. And since, what the Provinces got from Spain, they lost from time to time in their Freedom, Laws, and Privileges, <hi>Quantò quis obsequio promtior, opibus &amp; honoribus extollebatur.</hi> Base fellows, and oft-times strangers, whom none knew whence they came, beeing but once entered and settled at Court, were look't up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and held like pettie-gods.</p>
            <p>When anie State's-matters was propounded; the first care was how it would relish at Court. The State's interest came not once into consideration. Was there anie thing that meerly concerned either his Highness in particular, or anie of his hous and cold allies, that must bee dispatched forth with, not according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of the State, but in favor and to the advantage of his Highness, or his kindred and alliances.</p>
            <p>Let us but reflect upon <hi>England.</hi> At the begining those of the <hi>Parlament,</hi> as formerly the <hi>Scots</hi> also, were favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; but no sooner was the match concluded but wee heard another tune. Whatplots were therenotlaid? what practices remained unattemted to engage us in War against <hi>England? France, Spain, Denmark,</hi> did never so much as look about once in the King of <hi>England's</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, though near in blood, and Kings themselvs. Wee a Republick, of no kin, were haled along <hi>pede ligato,</hi> to provoke and attemt a Rupture, Indeed wee may thank <hi>Holland</hi> wee stand yet unengaged. How often and frequently, without anie notice given to the State, have our ships been attending the service of that King? what store of Ammunition; Officers, and Souldiers, have there been transported? What labor and industrie was there not busied by a certain man at <hi>Middleburgh,</hi> to engage <hi>Zeland</hi> in hostilitie against <hi>England,</hi> without
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165774:7"/>anie regard of hazarding the lives and estates of the Commons there, but onely to pleasure his Highness, and thus to plaie the master in <hi>Zealand,</hi> putting by his place a right honest, old, and honorable Council-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee-member, against all order and custom there, to seat himself in his room.</p>
            <p>In the Assemblie of the States-General, it went much alike in most things. Those of Holland have great caus to desire, that the State's Assemblies of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces may com to the <hi>Hague</hi> once, and look to these matters, and carriages; for their ordinarie Deputies saving but a few, evermore had their eie upon and steered according to the Court-motions in all delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p>The Queen Regent in France, though sister to the King of Spain, yet is too honest to have the least re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the interest of her Brother in prejudice to the State, where shee is seated; of that wee have seen proof enough these manie years.</p>
            <p>Here, on the contraie, the advantage and interest of this State must not bee regarded at all; but the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion is presently; Doth it concern his Highness, or the King of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Denmark,</hi> or <hi>Friesland?</hi> if so, that sufficeth; wee must needs steer by that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass, and by no means according to our own.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Spain, Portugal,</hi> at <hi>Brussels,</hi> at the <hi>Court of the Grand Signior,</hi> and elswhere, there is no scruple made of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of the Agents of the <hi>Parlament</hi> of <hi>England,;</hi> the <hi>particular Provinces</hi> have given publick audience to the same. But at the General Assemblie in the <hi>Hague,</hi> none durst vote the like; and why? Not to dis-oblige the Court forsooth. And yet they made no difficultie at all to give publick Audience to Commissioners of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165774:8"/>other neighboring States and Cities; and to the Scot's Commissioners also, assoon as they saw them disposed once to Treat with their King.</p>
            <p>But to those of <hi>England,</hi> by no means, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed had never been denied, had there not been that respect to his Highnesse's alliance, whereupon at last is followed that <hi>just affront</hi> wee received, by sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Ambassador <hi>Joachimi</hi> thus home again; which as much as in them laie, those of <hi>Holland</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently endevored to prevent, by sending over <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missarie Sharp.</hi> For it can no waies stand with the Commerce and Navigation of <hi>Holland,</hi> to bee in broils with <hi>England.</hi> But lo, this was so resented by most Deputies among the States General, steering ever according to the Court-winde, that they made it a <hi>State-treason,</hi> and <hi>Breach of the Union.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many other matters presented themselvs from time to time, which the Presidents durst not, for fear of displeasing the Prince? <q>And therefore was it an inveterate custom, that no President durst adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to com into the Assemblie, without repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the Prince first, and making him privie of all matters of importance, there to receiv, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to saie his Lesson.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And truly I cannot blame anie of them; for it is natural, that everie one love's and seek's to advance his Children, Brothers, Friends and Kindred; and there was not anie advancement almost to bee had, but by him and his means. But if anie have complied thus of meer design and malice, to bereav and despoil the Land of it's Freedom and Privileges, they above all others are unexcusable.</p>
            <p>Neither can I finde fault with his Highness; there
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165774:8"/>is not a Boor, Burgher, Gentleman, in Court, Town, Countrie, but strive's to advance his Fortune. The Monk or Friar would fain bee Abbot, the Abbot Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, the Bishop Cardinal, the Cardinal Pope. Greatness and Ambition is but an humane condition. His Highness saw <hi>homines ad servitutem dispositos,</hi> the opportunitie; and improved what others fitted for him.</p>
            <p>But now, that God Almightie hath delivered our Dear Countrie from that impending Servitude, and reacheth forth the golden Libertie from Heaven into our Lap, wee were indeed the most unthankful and abject people of all the world, if wee did not in all due manner embrace the same. Hee might well saie afterwards of us, <hi>They have forsaken mee,</hi> and give us a <hi>King</hi> again <hi>in his wrath:</hi> For the Scripture is plain, that <hi>Republicks are more acceptable or agreeable to God, then Monarchies.</hi> Which may well make us to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ponder, whence it is that som <hi>Ministers</hi> are such abominable flatterers; Sure Ambition lie's at the Bottom. Peradventure they will not have the name of Bishops and Prelates; but really, they minde the thing, they covet Autoritie. For, having the favor and ear of the Prince, they never leav till thereby they are impower'd to domineer it as well over their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-brethren, as in Civil and State-Affairs; like unto that perverter of Scripture, <hi>Teling</hi> in <hi>Zeland,</hi> and that Parasite, <hi>Sterremont,</hi> at the <hi>Hague,</hi> who, in the rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal of the circumstances of his Highnesse's death, and in the Pulpit, took upon him to prophecie, that the Prince's death was but the fore-runner of the ruine of these Countries. All good and faithful Ministers of the Word of God, may take warning, and bee sure that such Flattering, Court-hunting, Court-depending
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165774:9"/>Preachers do seek for somwhat els, then they can finde in their Bible; and that they do not follow the Lesson to bee <hi>like unto the least;</hi> but that they gape after the <hi>Surplus:</hi> that like the Bishops, <hi>quondam,</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> they may bee men of Autoritie, and bear swaie over their brethren, stooping to them to bee provided or advanced-with good fat Livings, lying in their Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. What bitter complaints there were taken up against such, by the better sort of Ministers in <hi>England,</hi> together with woful effects of such enormities is noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious: and wee have seen som copies of the like, not onely at the begining of the Truce, when <hi>Utenbogart</hi> for it was termed Pope at the <hi>Hague;</hi> but likewise at the begining of this Peace. For it is not Religion, but affectation of Greatness which haunt's these men, pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessing the good young Prince and his Confidents with such things as came short of heaven and earth, and which never entred into the thoughts onely of the good Magistrates in Holland and other Provinces; as if they should have gone about to alter the least tittle in matters either of State or Religion. What mean els these several blewcoat-books of <hi>Bicker's tumults,</hi> the <hi>Free Discours,</hi> the <hi>Bay-garland, &amp;c.</hi> but to render the Civil Magistrate, which found the Peace wholesom, Christian and necessarie for the State, suspect and odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and even to ass pers and blame the late Prince <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> himself, and the surviving Ladie Dowager (whose sollicitations of the Peace, and earnest painful pursu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof as by themselvs, so especially by my Lord <hi>Knuyt,</hi> hath been conspicuous) as guiltie of the same fault, which now they charge upon the whole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Her Highness self, and all the Hous of <hi>Nas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saw,</hi> do manifestly disapprove the extremitie of last
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165774:9"/>Summer's attempts; declaring their wishes, that it had never happened; and yet a <hi>Sterrimont</hi> and <hi>Teling</hi> dare take upon them to extol it; most impiously applying and abusing the holie Scriptures and passages thereof, to shelter their wicked assertions.</p>
            <p>Those that are invested with the Government, do not know themselvs yet to this hour, what mo ved his Highness to those strange proceedings, and these prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling fellows dare of their own haughtie ambitious spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit pronounce sentence; and know how to applie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to that no man know's, that which hath no beeing, and which none of all the rest of the pious, discreet and sound Ministers do meddle with, but are willing with everie one to remain ignorant of.</p>
            <p>The Governors of <hi>Holland</hi> nevertheless, are so dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and prudent, that they can wink at all, never troubling themselvs either to search into the causes (which cannot but bee vain and frivolous) or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what is past; it beeing apparent, that it is to bee imputed to nothing els but the bad counsil of his Highnes's consisting of the forenamed and publick Sycophants; but they declare, and make it manifest, that their aim is no other, but to maintein Religion, the Union and the <hi>Militia,</hi> together with all mutual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, Love and Friendship; inviting all the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces to repair by their States-Assemblies into the <hi>Hague,</hi> to advise and resolv together, of what may bee most expedient in the present high and weightie conjunctions. For then and there they shall see by their own eies into those upright, and peaceable intentions of <hi>Holland,</hi> in the behalf of a firm and unchangeable wel-fare, and prosperous condition of our common <hi>Father land,</hi> against all forreign and domestick, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165774:10"/>such flattering, venemous enemies, and haters of it's Rest and Unitie. And this is that heartie wish and desire of all the good ordinarie Deputies in the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralitie themselvs, as finding themselvs not warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and abhorring to bee led by the nose, and move at the book of the above-named, or anie such like flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers.</p>
            <p>If each Province shall bee pleased then, to chuse another Stad-holder for themselvs, either in general, or particular; they may dispose and determine, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one according to their pleasure. That lie's in everie one's brest and freedom; as also to impart such Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missions and instructions, as they think good them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selvs. But to receiv or admit of a Governor without instruction, without limitation, is absurd, and not practised in anie place, no not where Inheritance give's title; for even there are Capitulations, and sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulations made, and men do not blind-fold and hood-winkt subject themselvs to anie. Much less here, where the States of the Land themselvs are the <hi>Sovereign's,</hi> past all dispute, and acknowledged such by all the Kings, Princes and Potentates they have, or had to do withal. For which Sovereigntie, the good Commons of the Land have now these fourscore years so freely adventured, and contributed their Estates and lives, exspecting now at length som eas and reposal. But how will that bee compassed, when there shall bee no relaxation, whereby Debts may bee cleared, the Souldierie and other charges readily defraied, the Companies kept compleat and full, all the disorders in musterings redressed, as much as pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly may bee; for now it is too too bad and palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; Captains beeing through bad counsel, winked at by
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165774:10"/>the Court, especially strangers; to have them in the better readiness, and by them to Lord it over the States themselvs. Have not wee seen &amp; heard it, in the late Attempt and siege of <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> how the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie men began to brave and crow, how they triumphed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulted over the States, and trampled the Freedom and Privileges of the Land under their feet. All confidence between the States and His Highness was out of date; there was no trustie, familiar, and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate communication both with Militarie men and flattering Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; According to whose appetite and liking, new members be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to bee obtruded into the Magistrates every where, even and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, as if wee were no more a Republick, but down-right slaves. Whatsoëver was intimated, that it went not thus in other Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, greater and smaller, that was put by as mis-applied, wee want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed discretion, wee were unworthie to enjoie that Libertie, and those Privileges, that were wrested out of the <hi>Spaniard's</hi> hands; Hogs wee were, and to bee put into the stie, onely forsooth to make fat and great a small companie of base flatterers.</p>
            <p>Till God in Heaven above could no longer endure it; who now once again hath rear'd us up, and disintangled our feet, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our eies to see what wee lost. If wee are not possest now with a spirit of giddiness: if wee will not return to feed on husks; here is a new-creäted occasion for us to bee as true and complete a Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick as <hi>Venice, Genoa, Luca, Geneva, England, Switsers,</hi> and all other free Cities and placcs, and to becom masters of our own houses. Wee have caus still to look well about us; the flatterers are not gone yet, nor quiet, they have not yet forgotten the relish of the sweet morsel their flatteries procured them: if they can enveigle and hood-wink us again, they are sure both then and after to bee made much of, and to get as much as they are able to swallow, and bee the best and busiest cocks in the pit still. <hi>Sterrement</hi> and <hi>Teling</hi> will not bee long to seek for Texts out of the Bible, and rather pull them by the hair, and wrest them into anie <hi>metamorphôsis</hi> but they shall serv their turns, to Pope it among us.</p>
            <p>The question is, What wee should do then? That is answered by the Summarie above rehearsed, at the head of this Discours; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>That all matters concerning the State and the Militia, shall bee left in the usual cours and fundamental order of Goverment the several Counsels and chief Militarie Officers remaining in their respective Commissions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Manie of the Cities in <hi>Holland, Gelderland, Overyssel, Groningen,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165774:11"/>Zealand,</hi> and <hi>Friesland,</hi> have their own Election of Magistrates, and had the same under former Sovereigns; which Sovereigns, either of good will and freely, or for monie, gave up that right unto them. <hi>Groningen</hi> got it by capitulation of Prince <hi>Maurice Anno</hi> 1621. Everie Citie may now endevor for the like, so as it may bee don by the States, and have the stamp of Sovereign Autoritie. And why should not <hi>Middleburgh, Ziricksea,</hi> and <hi>Tolen</hi> enjoie it as well as <hi>Goes?</hi> Why shall not the rest of the Cities in <hi>Holland, Ʋtrecht,</hi> and <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megen</hi> have it as well as <hi>Horn, Enckbuyse, Edam, Munikedam, Arnhem, Zurphen, Bommel, Harderick, Kampen, Deventer, Swoll, Hattum. El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg, Wageningen, Geelmuyden?</hi> The Nobilitie and Gentrie in all the Provinces appear likewise, either by their Qualitie, or by a free E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of their own, and therein no Governor ever medled.</p>
            <p>To what end then should a Governor or Captain General bee requisite unless it were to command all the souldierie at his pleasure, and to force such Resolutions upon the States, as his humor prompt's him; and to bow and bend our Freedom and Privileges according to his own fancie, and then to return again to the old cours; No, not so, my Dear fellow-Patriots. In the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the War, the Governor had no power to dispose of Patents or Commissions; but with the knowledg and allowance of the States; but if wee creäte a new Captain-General, let us tie him never so strictly by Instructions, hee will, by means of the flatterers and other practises, never rest, til hee have wrested all the Direction from time to time into his own hands again, beyond all possibilitie to prevent it.</p>
            <p>And what need have wee of a Captain General? wee are in peace: <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France</hi> are in broils; <hi>Germanie</hi> hath laid down arms, being divided besides into manie pettie Principalities, Counties, Cities, standing in aw of us, and beeing ever jealous one of the other. Wee see no manner of appearance to draw us into the field; and if there should happen anie sudden occasion, wee have a Field-marshal, the Lord of <hi>Brederode;</hi> the General offices for the Hors, Artillerie, &amp;c. are well provided. How doth <hi>Venice, Swisserland, Genoa,</hi> and all these smaller Repulicks and free Cities in <hi>Germanie?</hi> not one of them doth so much as dream of having a Captain General, a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor, a Stad-holder. Hee that should attemt but to speak of such a thing amongst them would hardly escape to be charged with High Treason. The Kings of <hi>Poland, Denmark, England,</hi> might lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:165774:11"/>no Armies without consent of their respective States: no Prince nor Count of the Empire, neither, (but what is don by meer usurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) becaus that an armed Prince doth alwaies squecz monies from his subjects beyond all equitie and reason, through the instigation of flatterers, to enrich themselvs and impoverish the Common. One of the manie causes, why our fore-fathers took up Arms against the Spaniards, was, that hee sought to bring in Armies into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. So tender and delicate a point is that of Militarie Autoritie. And have not wee now much more right and reason to keep our Souldierie, which wee paie our selvs, in our, I mean the State's own direction, and not to temt anie with a new occasion of turning the same <hi>in nostra viscera,</hi> into our own bowels, as of late hapned.</p>
            <p>Can anie of the Nobilitie and Gentrie, can anie Citie-person rest secure in their homes and beds, as long as a General hath the power by secret and particular Pattents or Commissions, to command the Armie in one night, to bee at our Gates and Houses, and either by slight or force (both kindes have been essaied) to get into them. Truly no man can bee sure of pound or pennie, no not of his own life and safetie, or the best Jewel of his Wife and Daughters, if wee suffer the loos reins of Militarie Direction to abide in the hand of a Captain or Governor General. At Sea wee have very good Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Admirals, but wee are Masters of them, wee have the autoritie over them; wee must know where and whereto our men of war are emploi'd. The Prince being Admiral never went to sea, and yet by the Lievtenants wee see those services are well and gallantly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <p>Why may it not as well bee don by land, though now there is no need of anie; the most and main is atchieved still by dependent Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers. The King of <hi>Spain</hi> is so jealous of his own Generals and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, that usually hee changes most of them once in 3 years. The Archduke enjoies but <hi>Simulacrum Gubernationis.</hi> The King of <hi>France</hi> hath a new General stil for every Expedition, and several ones for several places. <hi>Venice</hi> and all <hi>Republicks</hi> are yet more circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect. <hi>England</hi> excused <hi>Fairfax;</hi> In a word, Every one is jealous of the Power hee own's, and loath to part with such a Jewel's absolute disposing, upon such easie terms, as wee did hitherto. Truly, when wee were under the King, wee had Stad-holders; and there was reason for it. Hee was absent, and had need of som in his stead or place, to manage the Government. And Hee changed them often. But here
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165774:12"/>the Sovereign, the States of the Land, are present themselves. It is absurd and against nature and natural reason for us to have Stad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders; All Nations, especially Republicks, mock and jeer us, like children, and fools, wilfully and knowingly running into slaverie. And now wee should prostitute our selvs much more, since by His Father's death there appear so many great Pretenders, which by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of their Experience and long services might bee fittest, &amp; would hardly brook it, every one to see that Honor enjoy'd by another; each one pretending to bee the neerest and the worthiest; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their jealousie, there can bee no better cours taken, then to let things bee as they are, and the highest Command where it is. The se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral great Pretenders beeing well provided and placed already, doubtless will bee well enough contented.</p>
            <p>But most absurd and inconvenient would it prove sure, to make the new-born Infant our Captain-Generall or Stad-holder: For, of Monarchies it is truly said, <hi>Wo unto that Kingdom, whose King is a childe;</hi> much rather would a Republick bee counted mad and frantick to chuse a Babe for their Stad-holder, Governor or Captain-General.</p>
            <p>This Infant-Prince will bee brought up by a Mother; whose Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies interest shall swallow up all other, and ever bee preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore these of our State, our Trade (the onlie support and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the State) and our own welfare. Hitherto wee were in som Mediocritie yet, but this Prince will bee Nephew to <hi>Spain,</hi> to <hi>France,</hi> to <hi>Austria, Denmark, Scotland;</hi> and under this pretext shall his minde ever bee harkning after a Roial <hi>Alterra,</hi> and after Majestie, and the ship bee steered still according to these Interests and intentions. Flatterers, <hi>Sterrem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nts, Telings,</hi> will not bee wanting. Haughtiness, ostentation, pomp, luxurie, riot, pride and wastefulness will invade the land ten times more and wors then ever. O let us avoid it, as the most dangerous Rock, that would split our Ship. Our condition would bee ten-fold more intolerable then ever it was before. It were better everie Province, saving their Privileges, had a Stad-holder apart; but best of all to bee and abide as all other Republicks. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheless the corruptions are so great in the world, the practises and subtilties so manifold, that, looking meerly on man's part, I have great caus to fear, wee may suffer our selvs to bee lull'd asleep again, and cajoled out of this so admirably-recovered golden Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; Which God in mercie forbid, and endue our good Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors with all encreas of Wisdom, Knowledg and Couragiousness.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>